<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A stop to the false characterizers hue-and-cry and a reproof to their unfruitful works of darkness. Wherein the folly of B.C. and L.K. is greatly manifested and their malice &amp; envy detected.</title>
            <author>Lamboll, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6349A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217572</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578206</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2616:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A stop to the false characterizers hue-and-cry and a reproof to their unfruitful works of darkness. Wherein the folly of B.C. and L.K. is greatly manifested and their malice &amp; envy detected.</title>
                  <author>Lamboll, William.</author>
                  <author>Buy, John.</author>
                  <author>Key, Leonard.</author>
                  <author>Coale, Benjamin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Sowle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: VVilliam Lamboll, John Buy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Key, Leonard.</term>
               <term>Coale, Benjamin.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A STOP TO THE <hi>Falſe Characterizers</hi> Hue-and-Cry And a <hi>Reproof</hi> to their Unfruitful Works of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Folly of <hi>B. C.</hi> and <hi>L. K.</hi> is <hi>Greatly Manifeſted</hi> AND THEIR Malice &amp; Envy DETECTED.</p>
            <q>The Soul of the Wicked deſireth Evil; his Neighbour findeth no favour in his Eyes, <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 21.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Wrath is cruel, and Anger is outragious; but who is able to ſtand before Envy? <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 27.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright men ſhall be aſtonied at this, and the Innocent ſhall ſtir up himſelf againſt the Hyprocrite. The Righteous alſo ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger. But as for you all, do you return, and come now, for I cannot find one wiſe man among you, <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 17.8, 9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> in the Year 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:172157:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172157:2"/>
            <head>To Faithful Friends (or others that make a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Truth) unto whoſe view the Pamphlet, called, <hi>The Libeller Characterized,</hi> hath or may come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore we give a particular Anſwer to the ſeveral parts of the fore-mentioned Pamphlet, we think it needful to give ſome Account both why we have for-born to Anſwer in hitherto, and why we have undertaken to anſwer it now, and the rather <hi>L. Key,</hi> (whoſe Name is to the greater part thereof) doth in his ſecond and third Pages ſay, <hi>That the Obſervations and Queries made publick, were long ſince delivered to ſome of the formal Preachers in</hi> Reading, <hi>but no Anſwer given to them.</hi> Now as for the Obſervations he mentions, we ſaw them not till they were Printed. The Queries we acknowledge were ſent to us in Manuſcript, incloſed in a Letter from him, bearing date the 7th of the 12th Moneth, <hi>83.</hi> On the 5th of the 1ſt Moneth following, <hi>Benjamin Coales</hi> (his Confederate in this Work) had finiſht his <hi>Hue-and-Cry,</hi> ready to be made publick, and on the 2d of the 2d Moneth <hi>L. K.</hi> had concluded his whole Work for the Preſs, as by the ſeveral Dates thereof appears: So that the time his Impatience complains of, as long, was leſs then two Moneths, and it appears by the date of the <hi>Hue-and-Cry,</hi> that there was preparation made for Printing ſoon after the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were ſent to us. And therefore if he urges our not anſwering his written Queries, as the Ground or Reaſon of his Printing them, he diſſembles, and is not plain. Now the plain Reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:172157:3"/>why we did not anſwer thoſe Queries of his at that time, was the Injustice and unfair dealing we had met with from <hi>L. K.</hi> and ſome others that took part with him; for beſides his reading a Paper of his own again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſome of us, he refuſing, with his Company, to ſuffer an Anſwer to be read thereto, he had before this ſent a Letter to one of us, namely <hi>William Lamboll,</hi> to which <hi>W. L.</hi> gave him an Anſwer in Writing, ſealed, which Anſwer ſoon after <hi>L. K.</hi> had received, he tore into pieces ſealed as it was, without ſo much as looking into it, to ſee or take notice what was written therein: Which rude, unreaſonable and unmanly Act of his (the Fruit of a froward peeviſh Mind, and of a Head-strong ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Will) made us think it not worth our while to write An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to be tore in pieces without being read. This was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we then for-bore to anſwer his written Queries, which we willingly ſubmit to the Judgment of Truth in every honest Friend, whether he had not thereby given just cauſe ſo to do? And we leave it to the Witneſs of God in every upright Heart, whether <hi>L. K's</hi> publiſhing what he hath done to the World, doth not proceed from the Spirit of the World, and ſavour more of Strife and Envy, than of Peace and true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Charity? And whether he hath not hereby added a further proof of Friends Charge against them of the ſame Spirit with himſelf, namely, that they are the first Publiſhers of Differences in Print.—And if any ſhould queſtion, Why we have not anſwered the Pamphlet ſooner after it was printed? Our anſwer is, (his <hi>Impatiency</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) we therein followed them wiſe man's Counſel, <hi>Prov. 26.4.</hi> we were not willing to be haſty upon him with an Anſwer, but to give him time to conſider at leiſure of that which he had haſtily and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly done, deſiring (if it would have been) that he and all others concerned with him in Speaking, Writing and Printing againſt the Truth and People of the Lord, might have received in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that ſentence of Condemnation that's due to their evil un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, that from a ſence thereof they might have repented of
<pb facs="tcp:172157:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>what they had done, and of their own accord have called in their envious and naughty Pamphlet; but inſtead thereof, after we had waited ſome Moneths, finding the ſaid <hi>L. K.</hi> to be very buſie and forward in ſpreading his miſchievous Pamphlet abroad in City and Country, and obſerving him to grow more confident, lofty, exalted and conceited than before, and having of late received from him another Paper in Writing (and of like tendency with what he hath Printed, in which he preſſes earneſtly for an Anſwer) but it being not made publick, ſhall take no more notice of it here) but ſay as we ſaid before, obſerving him ſtill to grow more confident, lofty, &amp;c. We remembred what the Wiſe Man ſaid, <hi>Prov. 26.5.</hi> For which cauſe partl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but principally for the ſakes of ſuch, who through weakneſs, and want of due conſideration, may upon the firſt view of his Queries and Obſervations, according as they are repreſented by him, be in danger of being miſled to think otherwiſe of things then in truth they really are, or that by our altogether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſilent, any ſhould conclude what <hi>L. K.</hi> hath written is juſtly charged upon us, the following Anſwer is now made publick by us,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Reading, <date>
                     <hi>the 25th of the 2d Moneth,</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Lamboll, John Buy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172157:4"/>
            <head>THE Falſe Characterizers Hue-and-Cry ſtopt, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Benjamin Coale</hi> and <hi>Leonard Key;</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE have read and examined your railing <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> which you call <hi>The Libeller Characteriz'd, or a Hue-and-Cry ſent after him, &amp;c.</hi> In the firſt Page where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in ſeveral other parts of it you charge ſome whom you call <hi>An envious Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Perſons, with abuſing ſeveral honeſt men, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Packets by Poſt, thereby.</hi> as you ſay, <hi>not only putting them to conſiderable Charges, but alſo abuſing ſeveral with ſcurrilous Language and Falſhood.</hi> What have been ſent by Poſt to you or others, of what Contents, or from whom, we neither know, nor think our ſelves concerned to enquire; ſure we are you never received any ſuch from us: And if any ſuch Packets have been ſent you by any Body elſe, it ſeems (ſo far as we can gather from your Words) to have been ſome of your own printed Books, or Papers, that have been written and publiſht by your ſelves, or ſome of your partakers, and have been returned to you again; for you mention printed Books writ upon between the Lines, and wrapt up in a blank piece of Paper. And ſurely if it were ſo, 'tis ſtrange you ſhould ſend forth a <hi>Hue-and Cry</hi> after him that helpt you to your Goods again. Men uſe to ſend the <hi>Hue-and-Cry</hi> after him that takes away their Goods, not after him that finding them ſtragling abroad, ſends them home again. And as for <hi>ſcurrilous Language</hi> and <hi>Falſhood,</hi> you ſpeak of; if that be it which you have printed in your 5th and 7th Pages, who-ever ſhall impartially view your Work throughout your Book, may clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee who the <hi>envious Perſon</hi> is, and whoſe the <hi>ſcurrilous Language</hi> is. For what Page is there in your whole Pam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hlet, that doth not ſhew forth both your <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Scurrilouſneſs?</hi> The Perſon that ſent you your Books again, is called in your Pamphlet <hi>[formal Apoſtate]</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172157:4"/>no leſs than five times in three Pages: <hi>envious Perſon, treacherous Perſon, Night Wanderer, one that cheats Men, little leſs than picking th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Pockets, falſe Tongue, one that like</hi> Lucifer <hi>thinks to make his Neſt among the Stars.</hi> This ſort of Language is to be found in your Pamphlet. And whether this be Scurrilous or no, let all that read it judge? And alſo, whoſe Tongue hath been moſt at Liberty? and who have ſpoken as though their Tongues were their own, without fear and regard? How often do you call that Perſon you are ſo angry with, (for ſending you Packets written between the Lines of your Book) <hi>Libeller?</hi> 'Tis the title, and common ſtrain of your Pamphlet, <hi>Libeller, Libeller:</hi> But who-ever it be that you mean, why do you ſo often call him <hi>Libeller?</hi> Is it only becauſe he ſet not his Name to the Packets, you ſay he ſent you? We can find no other Reaſon you give in your <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> but this: And this you ſeem to give over and over, and call him ſo often the <hi>nameleſs Author,</hi> as if ye feared you ſhould have wanted Matter to fill up your Sheet without it. And when you had thus vented your Enmity in part againſt him, then you Quarrel about your Money (your fourteen and eighteen Pence for Poſtage, as you ſay) and Wrangle about a Name, as though they were the <hi>two main things</hi> that troubled you. But that will not cover you, for in your 7th Page you ſay, <hi>Obſerve, ſo many as have an Eye to him, are zealous for the Form,</hi> &amp;c. What! do you know who it is they that are zealous for the Form (as you ſay) have an Eye unto, and yet do you not know his Name? Is not this an hidden Work of Darkneſs, thus ſecretly to ſmite in the dark? But through all your Coverings, the Light diſcovers you. You ſay in Poſtſcript, <hi>Here's a ſhort Deſcription of him.</hi> (meaning the Perſon that ſent home the Books.) A ſhort Deſcription indeed, but a long Villification, and foul Reproach. In the 2d Page thou ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, <hi>Benjamin, If this Libeller will come forth, and own his Work, he ſhall have a fair hearing.</hi> But we muſt tell thee, if he have, thou and ſome others muſt Repent, and amend firſt; for it is more then ſome of us can ſay we have had from you, ſince you have gone into ſuch Work as is here diſcovered. Further thou ſayeſt, <hi>This is to give notice, that whoſoever</hi> (mark the Word, <hi>Whoſoever;</hi> you intended your Pamphlet it ſeems for all ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) <hi>can give certain Intelligence of his Name, and place of Reſidence or Habitation, ſhall have reaſonable ſatisfaction for his Pains.</hi> And yet in Poſtſcript, <hi>Leonard</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is left to ſome that have made a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172157:5"/>great talk of their inward ſence, to make a further diſcovery of this name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Author.</hi> What ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ing and juggeling is here between you? Is this the way you intend to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e (who call your ſelves honeſt men) firſt to ſay, <hi>Whoſoever can give certain Intelligence, ſhall have reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſatisfaction;</hi> and afterwards ſay, <hi>It is left to ſome that have made a great talk of their inward ſence to make a further diſcovery?</hi> What, do you intend your Scoff at laſt ſhall be the reaſonable ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omiſe you made at firſt? Is that reaſonable? Is this like honeſt men, as you are fain to call your ſelves? Is this like men of underſtanding, which you are ſo deſirous to be taken for? firſt to propoſe it to <hi>whoſoever,</hi> and then ſay it is left to <hi>ſome:</hi> One while to <hi>all,</hi> without exceptions; and another while to <hi>ſome,</hi> and that with a limitation, to ſuch as have an <hi>inward ſence:</hi> What ſilly contradiction is this; are not you now found to be <hi>Libellers,</hi> who call the Perſon you write againſt, <hi>formal Apoſtate</hi> five times over, without any ſhew of proof thereof? And yet you ſay, <hi>You do not know his Name, nor place of Habitation.</hi> Your work is ſeen by them that keep their Habitation in the Light, to be a Work of Darkneſs, and the Fruit of Envy, Strife and Contention are in your Hearts, Rage and Anger poſſeſſes your Breaſts; your Spirits fret, and are diſquieted within you; Contradiction is among you, and the line of Confuſion ſtretched over you, for you are fighting againſt that divine Power that will be too hard for you, and all that riſe up againſt it.</p>
            <p>And now having thus far taken notice of the <hi>firſt Part</hi> of your <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> to which thy Name <hi>Benjamin</hi> is ſubſcribed, we ſhall go on to Anſwer the other part alſo, to which thy Name <hi>Leonard</hi> is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writ, or put. But in the way we take notice, that between your two Parts, there is this Scripture ſet down, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11, 12. To which we ſay, that as a Teſtimony, That we have no fellowſhip with your unfruitful Works of Darkneſs, we do reprove them; and becauſe it is indeed a ſhame to ſpeak, as well as a grief to think of thoſe things, which have been done by ſome in ſecret, we do in Modeſty forbear to mention them.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Leonard,</hi> to being with thy Preamble to thy <hi>Queries,</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>Here is the Work of a formal Apoſtate manifeſted, and ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and Queries made publick,</hi> &amp;c. Herein <hi>Leonard</hi> thou haſt ſaid true; thy Work is indeed the work of a formal Apoſtate, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172157:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Obſervations and Queries, which thou haſt made publick, do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently manifeſt it ſo to be: For hadſt thou not apoſtatiz'd from the Truth, and fallen from the living Power, and inward Vertue of it, into a dry withered lifeleſs Formality, thou wouldſt never have publiſht thoſe <hi>Queries</hi> and <hi>Obſervations</hi> which ſo directly tend to Reproach and Vilifie the People of God, and expoſe the holy Truth which they profeſs to the Scorn and Contempt of every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Reader. By thy ſelf therefore, and out of thy own Mouth, is thine own Work condemned to be the work of a formal Apoſtate, and therefore to be the leſs regarded. However, we are willing to look through thy Work, and manifeſt more particularly of what ſort it is; thou joyneſt thy Obſervations and queries together, ſaying, <hi>Some Obſervations and queries made publick, that was long ſince deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome of the formal Preachers in</hi> Reading. Now <hi>Leonard,</hi> we make no queſtion but by <hi>formal Preachers,</hi> thy flouting Spirit mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us two (for to us two thou knoweſt thou didſt ſend they Queries) whom in a lofty, but empty conceit of thy ſelf, being a powerful Preacher, thou ſcornfully calleſt <hi>formal Preachers;</hi> we ſee thy Sting (bleſſed be God) though we do not feel it; Thy ſcornful Spirit reaches not our Life, which is above the ſtroke of Envy. But <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> thou ſhouldſt have regarded, to have written Truth, which herein thou haſt not done, for though it be true, that thy Queries were delivered to us ſome time before they were made publick, (which how long it was, and why we did not anſwer them then, we have given the Reader account before) yet that the Obſervations (which make up a great part of the Pamphlet) were ever delivered to us before they were made publick, is utterly untrue, as thou thy ſelf well knoweſt. And therefore in ſaying, <hi>Some Obſervations and Queries made publick, that was long ſince delivered to ſome formal Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in</hi> Reading, thou haſt publiſht a plain Falſhood, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps is worſe than to be a <hi>formal Preacher:</hi> So that thy Work has but a bad beginning, and therefore thou canſt not well expect it ſhould have a good end.</p>
            <p>Thy firſt <hi>Query</hi> is, <hi>Was not Peoples going from the Light and Spirit in their own particulars many Ages ſince, the cauſe why ſo many forms of Prayers were made to be ſaid by the Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Query moſt properly concerns the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> what, and how many forms of Prayers they have, for what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172157:6"/>cauſe, and upon what occaſion made, the Church of <hi>England</hi> is fitteſt to anſwer: Yet this we ſay, (and you may do well to take notice of it) that the Form uſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of publiſhing their intentions of Marriage three times, and having a Certificate, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party live in another Pariſh, out-does, and condemns that looſe liberty, which ſome of thy Spirit have contended for, and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in. But ſince thou mentioneſt Peoples going from the Light and Spirit in their own particulars, we tell thee, It was they that went from the Light and Spirit of God in their own particulars, many Ages ſince, tht went out from the true Apoſtles and Church of Chriſt, into vain Janglings, Strife and Oppoſition, as thou and others of thy Spirit have done. And if thou hadſt not firſt gone from the Light and Spirit in thy own particular, thou hadſt never publiſhed this your envious dark Pamphlet, the Work of a formal Apoſtate.</p>
            <p>Qu. 2. <hi>And did not their Compelling, and uſing Violence to thoſe that were otherwiſe minded, proceed from the Spirit that made the Form?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Query as well as the former, relates to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who may anſwer for themſelves. Thy Snare is therein ſeen, and we may truly ſay of thee what <hi>B. C.</hi> in page 2. ſuggeſts of ſome (as he ſays) <hi>asks Queſtions to no purpoſe, except to ſtander and abuſe men.</hi> Such is this Query of thine concerning the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s uſing Violence (which concerns not us more than to ſuffer it, while others ſhrink from it.) If thou doſt not intend hereby to inſinuate, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> uſe Violence, then are thy Queries to no purpoſe: And if thou doſt ſo intend, then are thy Queries to an ill purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to accuſe, and not prove, to <hi>ſlander, abuſe</hi> and <hi>beſpatter,</hi> as <hi>R. C</hi>'s words are. Yet we do ſay, Perſecution and Violence proceed from that Spirit that is out of the Truth, which Spirit (as <hi>Jude</hi> teſtifies) wrought in ſome, in the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, that went in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> in Envy (which is the ground of Perſecution) as thou and thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have done in Printing, and ſpreading your ſpiteful envious Books (a means) to raiſe up Perſecution againſt <hi>Friends,</hi> and in the way of <hi>Korah,</hi> to caſt ſtumbling Blocks through your oppoſition and gait-ſaying to the Work of Truth, and orderly Proceedings thereof in the Church of Chriſt, which hath ſo corrupted the Minds of ſome that they have appeared in a light airy ſcoffing Spirit, which is both out of the form of Godlineſs, and contrary to the true Liberty which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172157:6"/>
            <p>Qu. 3. <hi>Did not the</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>with their Church-Faith, and Directory that they had made, do like the Church of</hi> England, <hi>when they had Power, Excommunicate, and caſt into Priſon ſuch as could not bow to their Image, which they had ſet up?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What the Presbyterians have done, hath been manifeſt, but what thou and thy company have done, &amp; are doing, ſome ſimple-hearted do not yet clearly ſee; but the day hath in a great meaſure to many, and we believe will more and more diſcover of what ſort your Work is, and what the tendency of it is, and what Spirit you are of, who endeavour to fill weak and unſtable Minds with evil Surmizes, jealous Thoughts, which you, with ſubtilty and craft, inſinuate into them, to diſaffect them to the work of Truth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in them, firſt a ſlight eſteem thereof, and then an open oppoſition thereunto, in which your Enmity againſt Goods Truth and faithful People, is no way ſhort of the Presbyterians. However, we obſerve, you here explain the Violence uſed by the <hi>Church of England,</hi> to be Excommunicating and caſting into Priſon, of which ſome uſe may be made hereafter.</p>
            <p>Qu. 4. <hi>Did not the</hi> Baptiſts <hi>with their Form, which they did cry up, do like the former? And hath not all the</hi> Lo here's <hi>and</hi> Lo there's <hi>ariſen when the People in every Generation have gone from the Spirit's Teaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether the Baptiſts did do like the former, that is, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate and caſt into Priſon, we cannot certainly reſolve; but we think thou haſt little Reaſon to reflect upon the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> about their Form, conſidering how formal and envious thou art thy ſelf; for there was a time when ſome of them were tender and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to God-ward, in the Practice of their Form; but thou and thy Company are found in the Practice of a part or piece of a form (which one of your company compared to your Marketting) in Strife and Oppoſition, and whilſt you are crying againſt all Forms; for have not ſome of your company preached, <hi>That the Way of Truth is without Track, like the way of a Ship in the Sea, and like the way of a Young man with a Maiden.</hi> Did not one of them ſay, <hi>If there were no impreſſion of</hi> Form <hi>left behind, he liked in well;</hi> And another, That <hi>he conſented to a Paper tht had ſome ſuch words in it.</hi> And on the contrary, have not ſome of you preached, <hi>That God is a God of Order,</hi> (as faith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>in all the Churches of the Saints?</hi> And hath this Order, in all the Churches of the Saints, no form? Had not the Decrees that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172157:7"/>were ſent by the Saints from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (by which the Churches were eſtabliſhed. a Form? And were they not of Gods Order? Doth not the Apoſtle ſay to <hi>Timothy, Hold faſt the Form of ſound words, which thou haſt heard of me,</hi> 2. Tim. 1.13. <hi>And the things that thou haſt heard of me among many Witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithful Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.2. Doth not the ſame Apoſtle write to the <hi>Theſſalonians, Therefore Brethren, ſtand faſt, and hold the Traditions which ye have been taught, whether by word, or our Epiſtle,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.15. And again, <hi>Now we command you Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you with-draw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the Traditions which he received of us,</hi> 2. Theſ. 3.6. Come <hi>(Leonard)</hi> conſider ſeriouſly of theſe things: Were theſe things which the Apoſtle exhorted to, and commanded, out of the way of Truth, or in it? We think thou wilt not dare to ſay, it was out of the way of Truth. Well then, if it was in the Way of Truth, was it without Track? Did it leave no Impreſſion of Form behind it? Was it like the way of a Ship in the Sea? How then could it be holden faſt? Now you that in words, for Contention ſake, cry out againſt the <hi>Lo here's</hi> and <hi>Lo there's,</hi> are not you in the <hi>Lo here's</hi> and <hi>Lo there's,</hi> one while ſaying, <hi>God is the God of Order, as in all the Churches of Saints,</hi> [There's one of your <hi>Lo here's</hi>] Another while ſaying, <hi>The way of Truth is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Track, or like the way of a Ship in the Sea, which is as the way of an Adultrous Woman that is without Order.</hi> [There's one of your <hi>Lo there's.</hi>] Thus you are unſtable, up and down, to and fro, toſſed about like the Waves of the Sea, divided between your own <hi>Lo here's,</hi> and your own <hi>Lo there's.</hi> The Apoſtle, who abode in the Doctrine of Chriſt, which brought People off from the <hi>Lo here's</hi> and <hi>Lo there's</hi> (but not from the Form of Godlineſs, for that he directed Believers to) ſaid, <hi>We ſee Jeſus:</hi> And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>While you have Light walk in the Light, leſt Darkneſs come upon you.</hi> Now had you ſeen Jeſus, and abode with him, who brings off from the <hi>Lo here's</hi> and <hi>Lo there's</hi>) and had continued walking in his Light, by which you were enlightned, you had not been found in ſuch Darkneſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Contradiction, as this before-mentioned, which ſhews you are gone from the Spirit's Teaching.</p>
            <p>Qu. 5. <hi>And hath it not been ſo with all other Sects, when they have erred from the Spirit, which was given to be for a Leader, and have runs into the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172157:7"/>ſetting up of outward things, which have proved a ſnare in all Ages; read and ſet how it was with!</hi> rael <hi>of Old, when they forſook the Lord, how did their Enemies prevailover them? Let it be a warning to all in our days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The beginning of this Query is, <hi>Hath it not been ſo with all other Sects, &amp;c?</hi> So! How? So as it was with <hi>Baptiſts, Preſbyterians</hi> and <hi>Church of England, viz</hi> to compel and uſe Violence, by Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating and caſting into Priſon, as the ſecond and third Queries expreſs (for theſe Queries hang all one upon another, and this thing of uſing Violence, Excommunicating and Caſting into Priſon, is the vein that hitherto runs through them all.) Now to this we ſay, We do not know that it hath been ſo with all other Sects; There hath been other Sects. beſides thoſe thou haſt named, which have not uſed Violence, nor caſt into Priſon, that ever we heard of; but thou ſpeakeſt of running into the ſetting up of outward things, which thou ſayſt hath proved a Snare in all Ages: They that have erred from the Spirit are in the Snare, though they never ſet up outward things; but otherwiſe to them that keep and dwell in the Spirit, the ſetting up of outward things hath not proved a Snare in all Ages. Thou runneſt too faſt <hi>(Leonard)</hi> to ſee thy way; The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> by the Spirit did ſet up outward things; did he, thinkeſt thou, ſet up a Snare? The ſetting up of outward things in the Error from the Spirit, is denyed; but the ſetting up of outward things in and by the Spirit, never was a Snare in any Age, whatever the Abuſe of it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward might prove. Thou biddeſt us read and ſee how it was with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, when they forſook the Lord, but thou doſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irect us where to read and ſee it. As formal Preachers, as thou repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt us to be, we can both read and ſee that thou doſt not divide the Word aright here: Doſt thou make no difference between ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of outward things, and forſaking the Lord? Which then wilt thou ſtick to, that <hi>Paul</hi> did not ſet up outward things, or that he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in forſook the Lord? That he did ſet up outward things, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks fully. One Inſtance of many may be given from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. And <hi>1ſt.</hi> where ſpeaking concerning the Collection for the poor Saints, he ſays, <hi>As I have given Order to the Churches of</hi> Galatia, <hi>even ſo do ye.</hi> And then goes on to direct the manner. What wilt thou ſay to this? Was not this the ſetting up of an outward thing? Did he forſake the Lord in doing it? We hope thou wilt be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, and rather acknowledge thy own Error in confounding
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172157:8"/>things that differ. Thy inſtancing <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old, to prove the ſetting up of outward things a Snare in all Ages, is a very unapt compariſon; for the Adminiſtration and Worſhip of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old ſtood moſt in outward things, ſet up by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Servant of the Lord. It is true, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> forſook the Lord, their Enemies did prevail over them, as your evil Surmizings againſt the Work of Truth, and you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Wills (your Enemies) have prevailed over you, ſince you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the Lord, and have ſet your ſelves in Oppoſition to what he hath ſet up: And did not he prove an Enemy to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſet up a ſeperate Altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> in ſubtil Policy to keep the ten Tribes from communion wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h their Brethren, the Children of <hi>Judah</hi> in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> under a pretence that it was too much for them to go thither, which indeed proved a Snare to them. And the made them a Feaſt, like unto the Feaſt that was in <hi>Judah,</hi> but it was in a time of his own deviſing. And ſo by rejecting Gods appointment, by going from that which God had ſet up, and ſetting up a Form of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing, not of the Lords ordering, but in oppoſition to that which he had ſet up, they became a Sect, and ſo were ſcattered from the Lord and from his gathering. And now read your ſelves in this, and let it be a warning to all concerned in our day.</p>
            <p>Qu. 6. <hi>And now it is come to the</hi> formal Quakers <hi>turn, and are not they, with all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir ſtrength and might they can get, in moſt places a ſetting up the form that they have made, and giving it higher Names than any that hath gone before: And ſome have had the confidence to ſay, and preach openly, (that what they had ſet up) was to keep things ſweet and clean, notwithſtanding many things have happened amongſt them in many places, which is a ſtink and a ſhame to mention, yet calling them holy Orders, and ſuch like names, as they, in their Imaginary Minds, could think on, too much like the Golden Image that was ſet up in the dayes of</hi> Daniel, <hi>which the Lord did and will confound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This being a long Query, had need be anſwered in ſeveral parts. <hi>Firſt,</hi> thou ſayſt, <hi>Now it is come to the formal Quakers turn.</hi> The <hi>Formal Quakers</hi> are in reality your ſelves, but we underſtand thy Speech, and know whom thou meaneſt by <hi>formal Quakers,</hi> even the Antient Brethren and Labourers in the Lords Vineyard, with all the faithful Friends, that having held faſt their Integrity to the Lord, have ſtood and do ſtand VVitneſſes in Gods Power, againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful creeping Spirit that hath got an entrance and habitation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172157:8"/>among and in you, and by and through you, endeavours to draw back the Lord's People from the true Order of the Goſpel, and from their diligent Care and Watchfulneſs over themſelves, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therein, into a falſe Liberty, and a licentious Looſneſs: Theſe are thoſe thou Stigmatizes with the brand of <hi>formal Quakers.</hi> And now thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is come to the formal</hi> Quakers <hi>turn.</hi> What is this [It] that is come to their turn, to uſe Violence, Excommunicate, eaſt into Priſon? This is, and muſt be the ſenſe of thy Words, if thy Words have any ſenſe in them: This String thou haſt harped on all along: This is it thou taxeſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> with in thy ſecond Query (<hi>Compelling,</hi> and <hi>uſing Violence.</hi>) In thy third, thou querieſt, <hi>Whether the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>did not do like the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which thou explaineſt to be <hi>Excommuncating,</hi> and <hi>caſt into Briſon.</hi> In thy fourth, thou askeſt, <hi>Did not the</hi> Baptiſts <hi>do like the former, which was to Excommunicate, and caſt into Priſon?</hi> In thy fifth, thou askeſt, <hi>Hath it not been ſo with all other Sects?</hi> which ſtill relates to the ſame thing (<hi>Excommunicating</hi> and <hi>caſting into Priſon</hi>) is come to the <hi>formal Quakers</hi> turn. This is a falſe ſuggeſtion <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> and of an high Nature: Where's thy proof? Whom have thoſe thou calleſt the <hi>formal Quakers,</hi> caſt into Priſon? Whom have they uſed Violence to? You and your Company's ſhutting <hi>Friends</hi> out of their Meeting houſes, and nailing up the Meeting houſe Door, looks ſomewhat like an act of Violence on your parts to wards thoſe you call <hi>formal Quakers.</hi> But what act of Violence have they done to you? Whom of you have they caſt into Priſon? Is not this ſuggeſtion of thine an horrible Slander? Is not this Libelling? What elſe is this, but as <hi>B. C.</hi> ſays in your Pamphlet, <hi>to have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled Tongue, tht will accuſe, and not prove, and ask Queſtions to no purpoſe, except to ſlander and abuſe men?</hi> Beſides, we cannot but take notice how ſlily thou doſt link together <hi>Excommunicating,</hi> and <hi>caſting into Priſon,</hi> as if they were alike evil, alike to be avoided and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: This ſavours of a looſe Spirit, that would tolerate all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly and ſcandalous Perſons in the Church, have none caſt out, how corrupt ſoever, which is the deſign of the wicked One, againſt which God's faithful People in all Ages have watched and warred, and at all times under every Diſpenſation, as occaſion hath offered, and need required, have uſed and exerciſed that juſt and neceſſary Power, which God hath alwayes inveſted them with, of diſowning,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172157:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and caſting out, and teſtifying againſt whatſoever was hurtful and ſcandalous to the Body; and this, how grievous ſoever it be to you, alwayes will be, as it alwayes has been in the true Church. And whereas thou askeſt, <hi>Are not they</hi> (whom thou ſcornfully ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſt <hi>formal Quakers) with all their Strength and Might,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſetting up the Form that they have made,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and giving it higher Names then any that have gone before.</hi> —We anſwer, Nay; there is in theſe Words of thine, a baſe Inſinuation: For neither have <hi>Friends</hi> made a Form, nor are they ſetting up any Form, but what the Power of god leads into; nor do the uſe Strength and Might outwardly, muchleſs are they getting all the Strength and Might they can in moſt places, as thou moſt falſly and enviouſly ſuggeſts, to ſet up any other Form but tht the Spirit of the living God in and through his People hath ſet up, as to his divine Wiſdom, ſeemed moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious and ſerviceable for his Truth and People, and by the ſtrength and might of his own eternal Arms of Power, he hitherto hath maintained, and will maintain and preſerve it againſt all the poyſonous Darts of every envious Tongue. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Some have had the Confidence to ſay, and Preach penly, That what</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">We neither ſet up nor contend for any <hi>Form,</hi> but what the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Power of God leads into, and juſtifies in.</note> THEY <hi>had ſet up, was to keep things ſweet and clean: Notwithſtanding many things</hi> (thou ſayeſt) <hi>have happened amongſt them in many places, which is a Stink, and a ſhame to mention,</hi> &amp;c. In this we believe thou ſlandereſt thoſe <hi>[Some]</hi> thou ſpeakeſt of: Who-ever ſaid or preacht openly, or privately, that what THEY had ſet up, was to keep things ſweet and clean; this ſounds like Truth, but like one of thy ſlanderous Suggeſtions. We own no Form or Order of Mens ſetting up, any further then men are or may be Inſtruments in the Lords hand. The holy God by his holy pure Spirit, hath ſet up his own holy Order in and among his People, and the end of it is to keep things ſweet and clean, and that's the Reaſon the <hi>unclean Spirit</hi> in you rages ſo againſt it, and them that ſtand up for it. And it any thing hath hapned, which is a ſhame to mention thou <hi>Leonard,</hi> if thou hadſt not been paſt Shame, might have been aſhamed to have ſo much as hinted it, knowing whom it will gratifie, and alſo conſidering how it hath been, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d is with many of that Party thou appears an Advocate for. Thou goeſt on, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172157:9"/>ſayeſt, <hi>Yet calling them holy Orders,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis thou, and you that in your ſcoffing flouting Spirit uſe to talk of holy Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ſay God is an holy God, and he is the god of Order, and the Order which he is the God of, and hath ſet up in his Church, is an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. They that love Holineſs, love it: They tht are for Unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Looſeneſs, contend againſt it. And <hi>Leonard,</hi> had not Envy blinded thy Eye, and ſtrangely clouded thy Underſtanding, even as a Man, thou wouldſt not have publiſht thy Weakneſs and Folly, as thou haſt done in this matter. If any thing hath happened amiſs among thoſe that profeſs the Name of the Lord, doth that prove either tht the order of Truth eſtabliſht amongſt us, is not Holy, or hath not a tendency to keep things ſweet and clean? Is the Scripture of Truth, or the Spirit of God e're the leſs holy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome unholy Profeſſors of it don't obſerve it, but walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it? Did not the holy Ghoſt in the Apoſtles dayes, ſet up an holy Order in the Church of Chriſt? Was not the intent of it to keep things ſweet and clean, and from running into Diſorder? Yet too many things happened among them that bore the Chriſtian Name then, which were a ſhame to mention: What! then doth it therefore follow, that they fault was in the Order, or in the ſetting up of the Order? Nay, rather is it not manifeſt and certain, that the Fault was in thoſe looſe diſorderly spirits, that like thee and thy Party, would not be ſubject to Truth's Order, but rejected it, and walkt contrary to it? Thou perſueſt thy evil ſuggeſtion, and ſayeſt, <hi>That this which thou haſt mentioned of ſetting up Forms, calling them holy Orders, &amp;c. is too much like the golden Image that was ſet up in the dayes of</hi> Daniel, <hi>which the Lord did, and will confound.</hi> But <hi>Leonard,</hi> was that which thou in deriſon calleſt the <hi>Quakers Form,</hi> and <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> ever ſet up under the Penalty of being caſt into a fiery Furnace (or under any outward Penalty) as the Image was in <hi>Daniel's</hi> dayes? Haſt not thou herein ſhewed thy ſelf to have too much Ignorance, as well as too much Envy? Beſides, they that ſet up the Image in the dayes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> were ſuch as had not believed on, nor known the true and living God: But they whom thou abuſeſt under the Name of <hi>formal Quakers,</hi> do both know him, and are led and ordered by him even in thoſe things that relate to Godlineſs and Chriſtian Charity among them as a Religious People; So here they Compariſon is Lame, as well as Malicious. And it is not thy crying againſt Forms in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172157:10"/>and comparing us with others in their Formality, that will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or excuſe thee and thy party in your unbridled liberty. Haſt thou forgotten how the ſame Spirit of Oppoſition in Truth's Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, did appear, and ſtrive and work againſt Truth and Friends in the beginning, much after the ſame manner as now it appears, works and ſtrives in thee and others, againſt Truth an the Friends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? For after Truth had been declared, and many convinced, and made a Profeſſion of it, then ſome turned from it again, and run out into a corrupt Liberty, and therein brought forth ſuch things as are indeed a ſhame to mention, and a grief to the truly Religious to think on: And then the Enemies of Truth appeared againſt the Work of Truth, bringing up thoſe bad Actions, which had been brought forth by ſome that had made a Profeſſion of Truth, and ſtung them at Friends, ſaying, <hi>Theſe are the Fruits of your new Light,</hi> &amp;c. juſt as you have done againſt the Work of Truth now, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where any have gone into bad Actions, <hi>Theſe are the Fruits of your new Orders.</hi> And thus you have judged and condemned the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becauſe of the diſorderly walkings of ſome; as thoſe in the beginning condemned the Light, becauſe of the bad Actions of ſome that profeſſed it: And here with Truth's old Enemies you have joyned, and have ſet up an imaginary falſe envious Judgment againſt Truth, which God confounded in thoſe before, and is alſo confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in you: And look to it in time, before it be too late, leſt you alſo be confounded in and with it.</p>
            <p>Qu. 7. <hi>And doth not many of the formal Preachers ſit with their Hats on, when many of the Lord's Servants are moved to Pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No; thoſe thou ſcornfully calleſt <hi>formal Preachers,</hi> do not ſit with their Hats on when the Lord's Servants are moved to Pray; but it is when ſuch as are not the Servants of the Lord (what-ever they may pretend) but his great Enemies, take upon them to Pray, That thoſe thou calleſt <hi>formal Quakers,</hi> ſit with their Hats on, as a Teſtimony againſt that envious and contentious Spirit, in which ſuch undertake to pray. The Lords Servants are ſuch as are ruled by him, and are found in his Work and Service, which is not a work of Strife and Diviſion, as you have been, and are found in. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>If I regard Iniquity in my Heart, the Lord will not hear my Prayer.</hi> But have not you regarded that Spirit of oppoſition and <hi>W. Roger's,</hi> and other pernicious Books brought forth by it (works of Iniquity) ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172157:10"/>heeply in your hearts, that you will rather deny us all, than you will give judgment againſt thoſe work of Iniquity; Nay, have not ſome of your Company been found in the like practice of keeping on the Hat, which thou ſo frowardly condemneſt others for? And thoſe of you that put off your Hats when ſuch as you call <hi>formal Quakers</hi> and <hi>formal Apoſtates,</hi> Pray, do not you therein act Hypocriſie? Is this the <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> you make ſuch a brawling for, to joyn in Prayer with thoſe you have rendred <hi>formal Preachers, formal Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Setters up of Forms of mens making, &amp;c?</hi> Are not you herein found bowing at that which you clamour ſo loud againſt? And is not this vile Hypocriſie and baſe Diſſimulation, to ſeem to own the Fruit to be good, even while you are rendring the Tree ſo bad?</p>
            <p>Qu. 8. <hi>And doth not many others imitate them in that ungodly Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? ſo that it maybe ſaid, as it was in times paſt,</hi> like Prieſt, like People; <hi>which is a trouble to many, and a ſtumbling block to the weak that behold it? And may it not be ſaid, as in times paſt, The Teachers of the People have cauſed them to err?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the weak ſees any imitating an ungodly Practice, they are weak indeed that will hurt themſelves with that they ſee to be Ungodly. And it ſeems it is thoſe that are in the Imitation, that are a trouble to many, and a ſtumbling to the weak, not thoſe that are in Reality. And ſo, thy ſecret ſmiting doth not reach us; but if the weak ſtumble and fall, it will lie at your Doors who have joyn'd to and follow'd that Spirit of <hi>Oppoſition and Contention</hi> (and thoſe in it) that hath cauſed Diviſion, and done Miſchief. And you that have falſly and maliciouſly rendred the Antient and Honourable in the Truth, <hi>Apoſtates, Innovators,</hi> and <hi>Incliners to Popery;</hi> whereby you have corrupted the minds of ſome, and given an occaſion of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling unto many: it is not your telling of Hats, nor your ſometimes uſing good Words, and fair Speeches to beguile the Weak and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, that will cover you much longer. And canſt thou expect <hi>Leonard,</hi> any ſhould think that thou haſt any regard to the Weak, who in your malicious Pamphlet in Print, haſt laid ſo many Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-Blocks in their way?</p>
            <p>Qu. 9. <hi>And do not ſome of the formal Preachers ſend great Packets by the Poſt, directed to honeſt Men in the Country, without any Name to them, on purpoſe to put them to Charge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any ſuch Packets have been ſent, they that ſent them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172157:11"/>beſt knows the occaſion and reaſon of ſending them; we are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to it. How comeſt thou to ſuppoſe they were ſent by formal Preachers, ſeeing thou doſt not know who ſent them? Mayeſt thou not be as much out in being ſo poſitive that they were directed to honeſt men in the Country to put them to charge, as thou art in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing they were ſent by ſome of us whom thou calleſt formal Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>Reading</hi> (for to us whom thou call'ſt ſo mal Preachers in <hi>Reading</hi> thy Queries were firſt directed and ſent, before they were printed, as thou ſayſt in pag. 3. And in the written Coppy thou ſenteſt us, they are directed to be anſwered by any in <hi>Reading</hi>) ſo that it ſeems as if thou hadſt thought the Packets had been ſent by ſome of us in <hi>Reading.</hi> But if ſo, thou wert out, for we ſent no ſuch Packets; nor do we think any body would ſend Packets by the Poſt, on purpoſe to put honeſt men to charges (as thou <hi>B. C.</hi> often ſuggeſteſt) without any other reaſon. But were not the Packets you ſpeak of, your own Books that you have printed and ſpread about the Countries? And have not you, and <hi>W. R.</hi> and others of your Company, expended a great deal of Money in printing and ſpreading your malicious ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and conceited Books? And although you have been at ſo much pains and charge to do Miſchief, we never heard, you thought much or complain'd of that; ſo that we may well think, your clamour about the charge of Poſtage, is rather to vent your bitter Minds againſt thoſe you call <hi>formal Preachers,</hi> than for parting with your Money, which at the higheſt Reckoning you have ſet down, amounts not to above 3 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> But it is moſt likely, it is your ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition open'd unto you in what was written upon thoſe Books, or in thoſe Packets you ſpeak of, that hath ſo much diſquieted you, tho now you go about to place it upon the charge, it may be, thinking that may have the faireſt ſhew in it, to carry off your work with a ſhew of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in your Complaint; but that Covering is too narrow.</p>
            <p>Qu. 10. <hi>And are theſe the Fruits of a Chriſtian Spirit, or from them that are apoſtatized from it? Let any that have any underſtanding of the things of God judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We don't think it the fruit of a Chriſtian Spirit for any to ſend great Packets by Poſt on purpoſe to put honeſt men to charge; neither is it at all likely the Packets you ſpeak of were ſent on purpoſe to put any of you to charge. To us it ſeems far more probable, that whoever ſent the Packets you mention, had a better end and purpoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172157:11"/>in ſending them, than to put honeſt men to charge. But you ſhould do well to conſider what Fruit of a Chriſtian Spirit you have ſhewed in taking occaſion from this 3 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> charge to publiſh your envious and ſcandalous Pamphlet to the World, thereby, as much as in you lies, making the Truth a Scorn, and the Profeſſors of it a Reproach, and a By-word to the Ungodly and Prophane, whom you have feaſted with your own Folly. Is this the Fruit of a Chriſtian Spirit? Let any that have any underſtanding of the things of God judge, whether you have not preferr'd your 3 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> before the honour of god, and the Proſperity of his bleſſed Truth? Had you been of a Chriſtian Spirit, you would have valued the honour and Reputation of Truth above Three Shillings and Eight Pence. But your oppoſing the good Order of Truth, your Writing, Printing, Publiſhing to the World your Malicious Scandalous Books and Pamphlets, your ſhutting Friends out of their Meeting-houſe, and denying them their Rights and Properties, are ſuch Fruits as ſufficiently demonſtrate to all that have an Underſtanding of the things of God, what Spirit you are of.</p>
            <p>Qu 11. <hi>And have not you, according to your Power, been like them before mentioned, conſidering your ſtanding, in giving bad Names, both in your Prayers and alſo Preaching, calling ſuch, dark Spirits (that could not joyn with you about your Forms) and that they were gone in the way of</hi> Cain, &amp;c. <hi>when you know in your Conſciences that many that you ſo brand, are blameleſs, both in Life, Converſation and Doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by [them before mentioned] thou meaneſt the <hi>Church of England, Preſbyterians, &amp;c.</hi> thou ſhouldſt remember, thou chargeſt them in thy ſecond and third Queries, with uſing Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and caſting into Priſon, which thou knoweſt in thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we have not done, and therefore not like them. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they give bad Names in their Prayers and Preaching we know not; but we know whom thou art like in thy fly Suggeſtions of Slander and Falſhood. What thoſe Forms are that thou haſt ſo o ten reflected upon us for, thou haſt not yet particularly mentioned; ſo thy general Clamour does but beat the Air: Thou ſeemeſt to run againſt all Forms, without diſtinction, as ſome others of thy company have done; one ſaying, <hi>The way of Truth is without Track;</hi> and another ſaid, <hi>It was like the way of a Young man with a Maiden.</hi> And if there be no Impreſſion of Form left behind,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172157:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>one liked it well; though it be contrary to the Scriptures of Truth, where the Apoſtle bids <hi>Timothy, hold faſt the form of ſound Words,</hi> And if ſuch of you as have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe things, and the like, be called dark Spirits, we think you have no cauſe to be offended thereat; for none but dark Spirits would ever have broached or held ſuch dark things as theſe; nor do we know or believe ſuch to be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in Doctrine (to ſay nothing of their Converſation) that hold ſuch dark Doctrines as theſe. Doſt thou think him blameleſs in Doctrine, that holds the Way of Truth to be like the Way of a Ship in the Sea, and the way of a young Man with a Maider, which the Scriptures compare to the way of an Adultrous Woman? Is this blameleſs Doctrine, or the Doctrine of dark Spirits? Dark Spirits indeed you are, who are gone from the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your ſelves, and are joyned to the Spirit of Darkneſs, which hath prevailed over you. So that what the Apoſtle ſaid with joy to the <hi>Epheſians, Ye were ſometimes Darkneſs, but now are ye Light in the Lord,</hi> may with grief be turned backward upon ſome of you, unto whom it may be as truly ſaid, <hi>Ye were ſometime in ſome meaſure Light in the Lord, but now Darkneſs is come over you again, and your Spirits are become dark.</hi> And though ye retain a Notion of the Light and Spirit to talk of, and deceive by yet the Work thereof you reſiſt, and ſet your ſelves, in your dark Minds, to oppoſe and revile what is brought forth thereby. And the ENVEY you have manifeſted, plainly ſhews you are going into the way of <hi>Cain.</hi> And the calling ſuch <hi>Dark Spirits,</hi> is not giving bad Names, but giving ſuitable Names to bad things. But ſurely if you had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to charge others with giving bad Names, you ſhould have forborn to have given ſo many bad Names your ſelves, as your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, in almoſt every page is ſtuft with.</p>
            <p>Qu 12. <hi>And was it not the Elders of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in days that are paſt, that gave unrighteous judgment, and did condemn the Innocent? And hath it not been ſo in our days? witneſs the Paper that was ſigned by ſixty ſix againſt their Innocent Brethren in the North? And may not the ſame Cry be ſounded in this our day, as it was then in the Ears of many, Return, Return to the place of Judgment, even to the Principle that was firſt preached, which was the firſt, and will be the laſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Story of <hi>Suſanna</hi> in the Apocrypha be true, it was the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (but in <hi>Babylon,</hi> mark that by the way) that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172157:12"/>in days paſt gave unrighteous Judgment, and did condemn the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent. But what then? thou askeſt, <hi>Hath it not been ſo in our days?</hi> We anſwer, No: In our dayes the Youngſters, and many looſe raw Lads have taken upon them to give unrighteous Judgment againſt the Elders, and have condemned the Innocent, witneſs the <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moreland</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> Papers, and thine, and others Papers and Books, ſince your oppoſition began. Had thoſe thou calleſt Innocent Brethren in the North, been truly Innocent, they would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their cauſe to the Lord, and to the Judgment of Truth in his People, and not have uſed ſuch ſubtil ways and politick means (with the help of others) to cover themſelves, as they did, witneſs the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> out of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> their fallacious Paper of Condemnation. The which Paper <hi>J. S.</hi> did ſeemingly, fully and plainly acknowledge to Friends at <hi>London,</hi> but when he came into the Country, a Friend of his, (or rather an Enemy) told him (in the hearing of one of us) it lookt as though he had recanted; whereupon he recanted indeed, that is, he denyed again what before he had acknowledged, by deviſing ſubtilly to put other meanings to his former words. But how comes it <hi>(Leonard)</hi> that after you have villified the <hi>ſixty ſix</hi> as Apoſtates, and the number of the Beaſt, and ſuch as have gone in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> that now thou counteſt them Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> eſpecially conſidering how ſlightingly and ſcornfully you uſe to ſpeak concerning Elderſhip, rendering it as <hi>Popery, &amp;c.</hi> Hadſt thou, and others of you, kept to the firſt Principle, you might have been preſerved out of that evil Spirit which hath led you to do ſo much Miſchief as you have done, for which you muſt not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the place of Judgment, but alſo feel the weight of Judgment, if ever you come to receive mercy.</p>
            <p>Qu. 13. <hi>When</hi> David <hi>kept to the Spirit's Teaching, did he not ſay, O Lord! thou haſt made me wiſer thon all my Teachers? and this taught him to order his Converſation aright; and it is the ſame at this day, and will remain forever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hadſt thou kept to the Spirit's Teaching, it would have taught thee to be wiſer than to write a Query (or rather an Aſſertion) to no purpoſe, except to ſhew that thou thinkeſt thy ſelf wiſer than all thy Teachers. We could wiſh thou wert wiſe enough to ſee thy ſelf, and ſome of them that joyn with thee in this thy pernicious Work, which you had never run into, had you kept to the Spirit's
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172157:13"/>Teaching. But being gone from the Spirit's teaching in your ſelves, and having ſet up your own Imaginations in the room of it, you are grown heady, high-minded, and hardy, to oppoſe and ſpeak evil of what the Spirit teaches, and leads others into.</p>
            <p>Qu. 14. <hi>And is not the Lord God, who hath an All ſeeing Eye, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made known himſelf in this our day, for this very end, according to his Promiſe, to gather a People to himſelf, from all the</hi> Lo here's <hi>and</hi> Lo there's, <hi>&amp;c. and all ſuch as they, abide under his teaching, need go no more forth, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the Lord God is appeared, and hath made known himſelf in this our day, according to his Promiſe, to gather a People to himſelf, this is certainly true; and hadſt thou kept to that which gathers, thou mightſt have been gathered, and kept near unto the Lord, and then thou wouldſt not have been found going forth in ſuch an unadviſed ſcattering Work as this that thou haſt publiſhed. But that which hath been a loſs to thee, and others that joyn with thee, was, your not waiting ſingly upon the Lord, to feel his heavenly Motion, that ſo you might have followed him witherſoever he goes, and into whatſoever he leads. But you have run with a <hi>Lo here</hi> into the Deſert, where Dryneſs and Barrenneſs hath taken hold of you, and Withering and Death is come and coming upon your, for which our Souls lament over you.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Leonard)</hi> having anſwered all thy Queries, we ſhall not need to ſay much to thy Obſervations, in which there is little but what hath been ſpoken to already. Yet we cannot but take notice how thou ſhuffleſt in thy Anſwer, about ſhutting Friends out of their Meeting-houſes, which it ſeems was mentioned in three particulars in ſome of the Packets thou ſpeakeſt of.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>firſt,</hi> of ſhutting the Quarterly mens Meeting out of the Houſe at <hi>Blewbery,</hi> thy Anſwer is, <hi>If is were ſo, the Friends at</hi> Blew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery <hi>can give the beſt Account why it was ſo.</hi> Thou needeſt not have ſaid, [if it were ſo] 'twas too notorious to be denyed or doubted; for they kept the Meeting-houſe door faſt lockt, and refuſed to let Friends have the Key, although two Friends went the Evening before tht if poſſible they might have prevail'd with them, to have lot Friends meet in the Meeting-houſe, as formerly, and they to meet with them; but inſtead of that they ſhut Friends out, and the moſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172157:13"/>of them went to your ſeperate Meeting at <hi>Reading,</hi> the which was wilfully propoſed and reſolutely carried on by you at the Quarterly Meeting before at <hi>Oare,</hi> contrary to your uſual courſe, and contrary to the Minds of the moſt of Friends that were preſent at the ſaid Meeting. And the beſt account thou or thy Friends at <hi>Blewberry</hi> can ever give of ſo bad an Action, muſt needs be a bad one. Thou ſayſt, <hi>It is a ſign they were a weary of ſuch company, which made it their buſineſs to brawl and contend againſt honeſt men, &amp;c.</hi> Brawling and Contention hath been your chief buſineſs in thoſe Meetings for ſome years, and we have hardly ever found you weary of that; but for them that are gone from the Life and Power of Truth, to be weary of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſuch as keep in it, is no great wonder. 'Tis the next In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>A. Eaſtmed's</hi> nailing up their Meeting-houſe door at <hi>Calne,</hi> ſo that Friends were fain to meet in the Street. Thou ſayſt, <hi>Whether it were ſo, or no, I ſhall leave it, it being without the compaſs of my Knowledge; but do wiſh he had not as much ground for what he did as they had at</hi> Blew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery. This is but a poor ſimple ſhift <hi>(Leonard)</hi> and it is greatly to be queſtioned whether thou haſt not belyed thy own Knowledge, or haſt ſome Equivocation or-mental Reſervation in thy Anſwer. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we obſerve theſe Actions are ſo black, that though you love to do them, you do not love to hear of them, nor are at all able to juſtifie them. The Lord give you a ſight of your ſelves, and a ſence of what you are, and have been doing; for of a Truth, the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit is entred you, and theſe are ſome of the Fruits of it. Have not Friends of late (if not at this very day) been kept out of their Meeting-houſes, and their Meeting-houſe doors nailed up by the Worlds People? And have not you done the like, and led them the way thereto? See now how you and the World have joyned together in one and the ſame Spirit, to do one and the ſame thing againſt Friends. Thus by your Fruits your Spirit is judged, and found to be the ſame with the Perſecuting Spirit of the World. <hi>But</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>What's all that to</hi> B. C<hi>'s Anſwer?</hi> 'Tis to B. C. and all the reſt of you, tht are liked together in that Spirit of PERSECUTION, and have joyned hand in hand, in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy againſt the Righteous. But if thou wouldſt have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that more particularly hits him, the other Inſtance does it; The ſhutting the Womens half years Meetings out of the Meeting-houſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172157:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>at <hi>Reading</hi> (which ſeveral of them had a Right in) which was his Act, and which it ſeems thou durſt undertake to defend him in. But becauſe the Women friends being ſhut out of the Meeting-houſe, were fain to meet in a Mault-houſe, thou ſcornfully playeſt upon that, in a frothy jeering Spirit, ſaying, <hi>I confeſs that was hardly well taken by thoſe that came from</hi> London <hi>and other place, to help to ſettle the Government of the Womens Meeting.</hi> And again, <hi>But he need not be ſo much offended with the Mault-houſe, for it is no ſuch inferior place to ſit in at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ummer.</hi> So here is <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the Perſecutor and the Scoffor found together among you, by which we hope, all Friends will judge what Spirit you are of.—And in the ſame flouting ſtrain thou goeſt on, for when upon your ſhutting Friends out of their Meeting houſe, it was queried, <hi>Is this your Liberty of Conſcience?</hi> Thou ſcoffingly anſwereſt, <hi>Surely the Women in the Mault-houſe in</hi> Reading, <hi>there met and aſſembled together, might have brought forth as good Edict as they did that met at</hi> Barbadoes. Thus, without fear or wit, haſt thou run on in a ſcornful, ſcoffing, frothy, looſe Spirit, uttering many unſavoury light Expreſſions, without Solidity or Weight, which ſhews thou art departed from the Fear of the Lord, and (art become Unſavoury Salt, the end of which thou may read, <hi>Matthew</hi> 5. ver. 13.) haſt no Bridle to thy Tongue.</p>
            <p>And in many places your Pamphlet abounds with Scurrilous Language, Bad Names, and Reviling Terms, flowing from that Gaul of Bitterneſs and Rancour of Mind that lodgeth in you againſt the Innocent. And as this on the one hand ſhews your Envy, ſo your ſtraining ſo often for ocaſion to call your ſelves Honeſt Men (ſuch of you as pretend to have Packets ſent you) which you do at leaſt eight times over, is a plain demonſtration of your Folly. The Wiſe man would have taught you better, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 27.2.</p>
            <p>Now having Anſwered plainly, without fear (of you) or flattery, the moſt material Paſſages in your Pamphlet, and cleared our Conſciences to you, we have done with you at preſent, till further occaſion be given. Yet in that Chriſtian Spirit that can
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172157:14"/>pray for Enemies, we heartily deſire that God will be pleaſed, if it ſtand with his Determination, to give you yet an Eye to ſee, and an Heart to Repent of the Miſchief you have, and are yet doing. This is our ſincere deſire, who are</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Lovers of Truth, Righteouſneſs and good Order, And Friends to all that are found therein,</hi> VVilliam Lamboll, John Buy.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172157:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172157:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
